Brookline, Mass. Leyden Congregational Church records, 1895-1975.
Congregational Library & Archives
Brookline, Mass. Leyden Congregational Church records, 1895-1975.
RG0701
Congregational Library & Archives
3.71 Cubic Feet
(4 boxes)
The Leyden Congregational Church in Brookline, Massachusetts was incorporated on November 24, 1896, with the cornerstone for the church building at 1835 Beacon Street having been laid on May 19, 1899. The Church eventually closed in 1975, after nearly eight decades of serving its neighboring community. This collection contains records on the committees and organizations, history, administration, building and finances, and church life of Leyden Congregational Church.
Leyden Congregational Church (Brookline, Mass.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by the Congregational Christian Historical Society in 1975; no accession number.
Historical Note
The Leyden Congregational Church in Brookline, Massachusetts was incorporated on November 24, 1896, with the formal organization of the church and installation of Dr. Harris G. Hale as pastor having taken place on November 4 of that year. For three years, services were held in the Beaconsfield Casino. The cornerstone for the church building at 1835 Beacon Street was laid on May 19, 1899, and the first morning worship took place six months later.
The building was restored in the late 1920s after a fire damaged the House of Worship. Still, the Church and its community celebrated many joyous events and occasions, including its 50th and 75th anniversaries. Beyond the administration of the Leyden Congregational itself, the Church led various organizations and committees. This included the Woman's Union, which was comprised mostly of women members of the Church. The Union carried out missionary and charity work, impacting the local and the international.
During its time, Leyden Congregational Church voted to ratify the "Basis of Union" in 1937 and joined the United Church of Christ in 1962. Leyden Congregational Church eventually closed in 1975, after nearly eight decades of serving its neighboring community. Today, the building at 1835 Beacon Street is occupied by the Chinese Christian Church.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains records on the administration, building, and finances of Leyden Congregational Church, including those from the Church's treasurer and Board of Trustees. The collection also holds records on church life and history, which feature a scrapbook as well as materials on the Church's 40th, 50th, and 75th, anniversaries. Finally, in this collection there are records on the committees and organizations associated with Leyden Congregational, such as their Woman's Union.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into five series. The second and third series have been further arranged into three and six sub-series, respectively. Records in each series and sub-series have been arranged by topic and in chronological order.
Church anniversaries.; Church finance.; Church history.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Women in missionary work.; Women -- Societies and clubs.; Hale, Harris, 1865-1945; Leyden Congregational Church (Brookline, Mass.)
- Committee records, 1895 1975; 1895-1975; 17 Folders
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records from various organizations within and connected to the Leyden Congregational Church, including the Building Committee, Church Committee, Church Council, Ecclesiastical Council, Music Committee, Prudential Board, and Woman's Union.
  - Building Committee records, 1895 1925; 1895-1925 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Building Committee records, 1898 1899; 1898-1899 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Church Committee records, 1896 1903; 1896-1903 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Church Committee records, 1900 1925; 1900-1925 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Church Committee records, 1964 1965; 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Church Council meeting minutes, 1895 1899; 1895-1899 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Copy of Ecclesiastical Council meeting minutes, 1896 1924; 1896-1924 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Music Committee records, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Woman's Union records, 1896 1903; 1896-1903 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Woman's Union records, 1898 1912; 1898-1912 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Woman's Union Social Department records, 1901 1913; 1901-1913 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Woman's Union records, 1911 1975; 1911-1975; 1968 1975; 1968-1975 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Woman's Union financial records, 1965 1970; 1965-1970 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Woman's Union and Mary Crosby records, 1936 1964; 1936-1964 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Woman's Union and Mary Crosby records, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Prudential Board meeting minutes, 1966 1974; 1966-1974 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Prudential Board meeting minutes, 1966 1975; 1966-1975 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Church History, 1896 1974; 1896-1974; 8 Folders; 1 Volume
  This series contains records on the anniversaries and history of Leyden Congregational Church, as well as books of remembrance.
  - Histories, 1896 1949; 1896-1949; 2 Folders
    This sub-series contains a scrapbook and other records on the history of Leyden Congregational Church.
    - Church histories, 1896 1949; 1896-1949 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Scrapbook, 1932 1933; 1932-1933 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Anniversaries, 1936 1971; 1936-1971; 5 Folders
    This sub-series contains records and correspondence pertaining to the 40th, 50th, and 75th anniversaries of the Leyden Congregational Church.
    - 40th Anniversary records, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 50th Anniversary correspondence, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 50th Anniversary records, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - 75th Anniversary correspondence, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 75th Anniversary records, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Remembrances, 1954 1974; 1954-1974; 1 Folder; 1 Volume
    This sub-series contains books of remembrances from the Leyden Congregational Church.
    - Book of Remembrance, 1954 1968; 1954-1968 (Box 4, Volume 1)
    - Remembrances, 1958 1974; 1958-1974 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Church Administration, 1896 1975; 1896-1975; 43 Folders; 4 Volumes; 2 Items
  This series contains annual reports, bylaws and their proposed revisions, and records pertaining to the Board of Trustees, clerks, and ministers of the Leyden Congregational Church.
  - Membership and Vital records, 1896 1975; 1896-1975; 4 Volumes; 2 Items
    This sub-series contains membership records from the Leyden Congregational Church, beginning in 1896.
    - Membership records, 1896 1948; 1896-1948 (Box 1, Volume 1)
    - Membership records, 1896 1973; 1896-1973 (Box 2, Volume 1)
    - Membership records, 1946 1960; 1946-1960 (Box 2, Volume 2)
    - Membership records, 1949 1955; 1949-1955 (Box 2, Volume 3)
    - Membership records, through 1974 (Box 4, Item 1)
      This collection of membership cards ends in 1974. A start date is unknown.
    - Membership records, after 1975 (Box 4, Item 2)
      This collection of membership cards starts in 1975. An end date is unknown.
  - Annual reports, 1897 1973; 1897-1973; 9 Folders
    This sub-series contains annual reports for the Leyden Congregational Church from 1897 to 1973.
    - Annual report, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Annual report, 1898 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Annual report, 1899 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Annual report, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Annual reports, 1927 1949; 1927-1949 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Annual reports, 1950 1974; 1950-1974 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Annual reports, 1965 1967; 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Annual reports, 1967 1970; 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Annual reports, 1967 1973; 1967-1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clerk's records, 1924 1967; 1924-1967; 3 Folders
    This sub-series contains clerk's records from the Leyden Congregational Church from 1924 to 1967.
    - Clerk's records, 1924 1941; 1924-1941 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Clerk's records, 1942 1954; 1942-1954 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Clerk's records, 1955 1967; 1955-1967 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Ministerial records, 1927; 1964; 2 Folders
    This sub-series contains ministerial records from the Leyden Congregational Church as well as records from the Old South Church in Boston, Massachusetts.
    - Old South Church records, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Ministerial records, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Board of Trustees records, 1928 1971; 1928-1971; 27 Folders
    This sub-series contains meeting minutes, records, and correspondence from the Board of Trustees of the Leyden Congregational Church, as well as records on the New Perspectives School.
    - Board of Trustees meeting minutes, 1928 1938; 1928-1938 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Board of Trustees meeting minutes, 1960 1966; 1960-1966 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Board of Trustees meeting minutes, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Board of Trustees meeting minutes, 1964 1965; 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Board of Trustees meeting minutes, 1964 1966; 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Board of Trustees meeting minutes, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Board of Trustees meeting minutes, 1966 1968; 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Board of Trustees meeting minutes, 1966 1970; 1966-1970 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Board of Trustees meeting minutes, 1966 1971; 1966-1971 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Board of Trustees meeting minutes, 1966 1973; 1966-1973 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Board of Trustees meeting minutes, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Board of Trustees records, 1928 1929; 1928-1929 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Board of Trustees records, 1940 1960; 1940-1960 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Board of Trustees records, 1957 1962; 1957-1962 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Board of Trustees records, 1962 1964; 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Board of Trustees records, 1965 1970; 1965-1970 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Board of Trustees records, 1966 1968; 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Board of Trustees property records, 1945 1960; 1945-1960 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Board of Trustees Treasurer's Bonds records, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Board of Trustees Heating Equipment records, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Board of Trustees House Committee records, 1957 1959; 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Board of Trustees correspondence, 1949 1951; 1949-1951 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Board of Trustees correspondence, 1953 1960; 1953-1960 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Board of Trustees correspondence, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Board of Trustees correspondence, 1957 1964; 1957-1964 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Board of Trustees and Town of Brookline correspondence, 1953 1960; 1953-1960 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - New Perspectives School records, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Bylaws and Proposed Revisions, 1931 1966; 1931-1966; 2 Folders
    This sub-series contains the bylaws and proposed revisions of the bylaws of the Leyden Congregational Church from 1931 to 1966.
    - Bylaws and Proposed Revisions, 1931; 1963 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Bylaws and Proposed Revisions, 1965 1966; 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Building and Finance records, 1901 1974; 1901-1974; 6 Folders
  This series contains building and finance records for Leyden Congregational Church. These records include a an article of the restoration of the church building, a copy of the church charter, deeds, treasurer reports, and trust funds.
  - Church deeds, 1901; 1960 1961; 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Trust Funds, 1903 1940; 1903-1940 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Annual Treasurer reports, 1927; 1930 1947; 1930-1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Article on Building Restoration, October 19, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Annual Treasurer report, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Copy of Church Charter, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Church Life, 1926 1967; 1926-1967; 4 Folders
  This series contains a report from the Choral Club, parish correspondence, an obituary on former minister Harris G. Hale, and canvassing records of the Leyden Congregational Church.
  - Choral Club report, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Parish correspondence, 1926 1966; 1926-1953, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Ministry of Harris G. Hale, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Every Member Canvass" records, 1956 1967; 1956-1967 (Box 2, Folder 4)